All right, so in the midst of the metric
buttload of activism going on in the
1960s and 70s, you didn't think
Americans weren't going to turn that
activist urge toward environmental
problems, did you? Don't be crazy.
>> No, environmentalists are about to have
their moment, y'all, and it's time we
talked about it. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked Silent Spring
style, let's get to it. Okay, so first
of all, you need to understand the
context for the rise of the
Environmental Protection Movement, and
that context was largely made up of the
desire to create a national energy
policy for the United States. So, in
case you missed it over the last few
videos, let me say it plain. Over the
course of the 20th century, the United
States was becoming deeply dependent on
oil as its main source of energy. And a
big honking reason for that was the
growth and adoption of the automobile as
Americans' main mode of transportation.
And with more and more suburban
Americans needing to drive to work, the
health of the economy was real tied up
in a steady flow of oil coming into the
country. And that was fine because by
the 1970s, the vast majority of the
world's oil was supplied by a handful of
Middle Eastern countries. And these
countries banded together to form the
Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries, through which they exercised
substantial global economic power by
setting prices for their exported oil.
And hey, no problems there because by
the 1970s, the global economy encouraged
states to specialize in producing and
exporting what they were best at
producing and exporting, and then
relying on the exports of other
countries to supply all the goods that
they needed. And so, this relationship
allowed the United States to import all
the oil that it needed to keep its late
20th century industrial economy cranking
because they could import the oil far
cheaper than they could drill it out of
the US soil. But then, things kind of
fell apart in 1973 when OPEC went ahead
and slapped the United States with an
oil embargo in order to punish them for
supporting Israel during the Yom Kippur
War. As it turned out, Israel fought
against a coalition of Arab countries
during that war, some of whom were OPEC
members, and they were not that fond of
America supporting their enemies. And
so, as a result of the embargo, oil
prices shot up, and that led to a severe
shortage in the United States. And this
had the effect of crippling
oil-dependent industries, as well as
significantly raising prices on gasoline
for cars, and all of that led to
inflation and rising unemployment. And
to put it mildly, that was not a good
economic situation. What I mean is, the
oil embargo, combined with various other
factors, led the US economy into a
debilitating slump that became known as
stagflation, which was a novel
combination of stagnant employment
numbers and rising inflation. And
economists were flummoxed. Flummoxed, I
tell you, because they had never seen
such a thing. And therefore, they had an
awful time understanding how to pull the
economy out of the situation because
none of the standard economic remedies
would work. Like in the past, if
policymakers wanted to fix inflation,
then their efforts usually resulted in
increased unemployment. But if they
wanted to fix unemployment, then that
usually resulted in higher inflation.
And that's fine if you're dealing with
one problem at a time, but in
stagflation, both problems were present,
and it seemed to be an unfixable
economic conundrum. And so, because of
the profound effects the oil crisis had
on the American economy, some
policymakers decided that it was time
for the United States to create a
national energy policy. And to that end,
President Jimmy Carter signed a law in
1977, which created a new executive
department, namely the Department of
Energy. And its job was to support
research and development to explore
national strategies both to conserve
energy and find alternative energy
sources that would help the US become
less vitally dependent on foreign oil.
Okay, so that's the context, and now
let's talk about the effects of this
whole mess. So, the oil crisis only
confirmed the conviction among
environmentally minded Americans that
the Earth's resources were limited and
thus must be protected, and that gave
birth to a significant movement to
protect and preserve the natural
ecosystems of the American continent.
Now, while environmentalism had a long
history in American policy, the older
style conservation focused more on
creating national parks and protecting
physical spaces. However, the
environmentalism of the 1970s focused
less on protecting specific physical
spaces and more on preserving the wider
ecosystem in which all species and
places live together in mutual
interdependence. And that particular
emphasis became popular with the
publication of Rachel Carson's 1962 book
Silent Spring. In this book, Carson
demonstrated how the widespread use of
synthetic pesticides in industrial-scale
agriculture, especially DDT, led to
catastrophic environmental effects. She
found through her research that these
pesticides don't simply disappear after
they're sprayed, but instead linger in
the environment and cause irreparable
harm to the species, both animal and
human alike, who depend on the resources
of that ecosystem. For example, a
serious concern to Carson was that birds
drank water and ate food contaminated
with DDT, and that led to weakened eggs,
and if left unchecked, the likely
disappearance of the bird population
altogether. And that's what the Silent
Spring was referring to, a spring season
in which there were no longer any bird
songs because their population had been
destroyed by the indiscriminate use of
chemicals. And that would be, to
paraphrase Carson, a serious bummer.
However, the aforementioned hypothetical
bummer did not, in fact, occur because
DDT was banned in 1972 after a committee
investigated her findings and found them
all together credible. Okay, now while
Carson's book galvanized many Americans
who already leaned toward environmental
conservation, the movement wouldn't
really gain a critical mass of popular
support until the 1970s. And that's
because it was a decade packed with very
public environmental disasters that got
the attention of the American public,
and I'll give you three examples of
these nasties. First of all, there was
the Cuyahoga River fire in 1969. And no,
I didn't stutter, a river caught fire.
So, by 1969, the Cuyahoga River in Ohio
was considered one of the most polluted
rivers in America. In fact, it was so
polluted that over the course of the
20th century, the river had caught fire
more than a dozen times. Look, I don't
know about you, but I'm pretty
comfortable with a river catching fire
like, I don't know, five or six times,
but more than a dozen times? Well,
that's too much. Anyway, the 1969 fire
gained national attention thanks to a
story written in the very popular Time
magazine. And as problems like these
gained more national attention, polling
numbers showed that a majority of
Americans were concerned about
environmental issues and wanted the
government to take steps to intervene.
And probably the biggest response here
was President Nixon's establishment of
the Environmental Protection Agency in
1971. It was a government that was
responsible for regulating activities
that resulted in pollution or other
kinds of potential environmental harm.
And hey, that's a great move, but even
so, examples of the consequences of
harming the environment just kept coming
in this decade. And that leads me to the
second example of environmental disaster
in the 1970s, namely the contamination
of the Love Canal. So, in Niagara Falls,
New York, it was discovered that an
industrial corporation had buried tons
of toxic waste into the bed of Love
Canal before it was completed. And over
time, the toxins had leaked into a
nearby neighborhood, causing high rates
of cancer and frequent miscarriages and
an unusual amount of birth defects among
the residents. And that ultimately led
President Carter to sign into law what
became known as the EPA Superfund, which
allocated money to clean up and
decontaminate sites like Love Canal that
had been harmed by chemical waste. And
finally, the third example of
environmental disaster was the Three
Mile Island incident. So, as if
Americans needed any further reason to
support environmental conservation
legislation, they got yet one more in
1979. So, in that year, a nuclear power
plant on Three Mile Island in
Pennsylvania experienced a partial
meltdown and as a result, released
radioactive chemicals into the
environment, which happened to be in
close proximity to a highly populated
town. However, to be fair, officials
quickly responded and kept the reactor
from exploding, which would have created
a much larger and more dangerous
chemical fallout. But regardless,
despite the fact that nuclear energy was
much cleaner than burning fossil fuels
and represented a promising path toward
American energy independence, this
disaster seriously slowed the wider
adoption of nuclear power. Okay, you can
click here to watch all my other Unit 8
videos, or you can click here to grab my
A Push Heimler Review Guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I'm glad you came around, and
I'll catch on the flip-flop. I'm out.